<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A shield against the Parthian dart, or, A word to the purpose, shot into Wallingford-House. Answered in defence of the present actions of state here in England, that produced the late change of government. By J.S.</title>
            <author>Streater, John, fl. 1650-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E988_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867074</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94044)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E988[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A shield against the Parthian dart, or, A word to the purpose, shot into Wallingford-House. Answered in defence of the present actions of state here in England, that produced the late change of government. By J.S.</title>
                  <author>Streater, John, fl. 1650-1670.</author>
                  <author>Spittlehouse, John, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.S. = John Streater.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: A word to purpose.</note>
                  <note>The appendix is a reply to: Anglesey, Arthur Annesley, Earl of.  England's confusion.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Spittlehouse.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglesey, Arthur Annesley, --  Earl of, 1614-1686. --  England's confusion.</term>
               <term>Word to purpose.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168631:1"/>
            <p>A SHIELD Againſt the Parthian Dart, <hi>OR, A</hi> WORD to the Purpoſe, <hi>SHOT INTO</hi> Wallingford-Houſe.</p>
            <p>Anſwered in Defence of the preſent ACTIONS of STATE here in <hi>England,</hi> that produced the late Change of GOVERNMENT.</p>
            <p>By J. S.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168631:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168631:2"/>
            <head>A Shield againſt the <hi>Parthian Dart.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PAge the 10th, the Authour hath this Quaere, upon which he raiſeth his Inſuing Diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the Men met together at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (where the <hi>Commons</hi> uſe to meet) be at this day a <hi>Lawfull Parliament,</hi> according to the Fundamental Laws of this Nation, to bind the People to obey their Commands?</p>
            <p>He admitteth, That power derived from the People, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a Supremacy; and that it is fixed ſomewhere there, in one or more; and that the <hi>Commons</hi> did, and had power to, Elect a Repreſentative; though they were formerly known by no other names then Petitioners. I ſhall briefly anſwer every particular; and then Aſſert a general defence of the now-Sitting of the Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> whom God direct, and preſerve.</p>
            <p>That the Commons were ſometimes Petitioners to the Kings of this Nation, I grant; but from thence it is not to be inferr'd, That what they petitioned for, if it were refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the King, that they could not command it: they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver petitioned the King but in caſe of obſtinacy; as in the caſe of the <hi>Petition of Right:</hi> the Parliament when they could not draw the King to conſent to the thing propounded by Argument, they did by Prayer entreat or Petition. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did ſo, it doth not therefore argue, That the King's power was ſuperiour to the Parliament; for that the Kings power of Conſenting to the Paſſing of Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, was no other than as if <hi>A.</hi> ſhould make a Letter of Attorney to <hi>B: B.</hi> refuſeth to Act by that Authority <hi>A.</hi> giveth him by vertue of that Letter of Atturney: therefore he intreateth and prayeth <hi>B.</hi> to accept of the Letter of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, and to act by it: <hi>B.</hi> conſulteth his own Intereſt, and ſaith, If it be made in ſuch and ſuch a manner and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168631:3"/> form, I will act by it. <hi>A.</hi> finding that <hi>B.</hi> is the fitteſt perſon either living upon the place where it is to be put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or for ſome other Reaſons, condeſcendeth to <hi>B.</hi> Even ſo, hath it been in times paſt between the King and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The People Repreſented in Parliament, make Laws or Letters of Atturney to their ſtanding Officer, the King, for which he received his Fees, the Revenues of the Crown, and was their Atturney: He having by ſeveral deſcents gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned footing upon the Intereſt of the People, ſtandeth upon his Tearms, and will not accept of Laws made in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or in that manner, but conſulteth his own Intereſt: the Parliament ſeeing that it is convenient to have their Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney's Conſent or Opinion, do apply themſelves to him by Petition or Intreaty. This doth not argue, but that the power is in thoſe who Grant or Appoint; and, that he that is to put it in Execution, is any other but the Inferiour to that power: the Petition or Intreaty doth not make him Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour. To this purpoſe, ſee Sir <hi>Ed Coke,</hi> chap. <hi>High-Courts of Parliament, folto</hi> 14. The Lords and Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, upon demand of Ayd in the behalf of the King by any new Device; anſwered, That they tendered the King's Eſtate, but they could not conſent to this new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, without Conference with their Counties, for which they ſerved; This (ſaith he) is the ancient Cuſtome of Parliaments, and it is according to Law.</p>
            <p>That the Great Councel of the <hi>Commons</hi> is much more Ancient than theſe Petitions ſpoken of by the Authour, is evident by <hi>Tacitus</hi> in the Life of <hi>Agricola;</hi> ſpeaking how eaſily the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Princes were overcome by the <hi>Romans;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>It was becauſe they did not conſult with their Common-Councel.</hi> Time by th' Events hath Reproved that mode of Petitioning; for it was the occaſion of the claiming of a <hi>Negative Voyce,</hi> unto which the Kings had no Right at all. But it may be Objected, That an Atturney hath a Negative Voyce, Why ſhould not the King alſo have the ſame? To
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168631:3"/> which I anſwer, That one that is not bound by his Office, 'tis true, may refuſe to accept of that Authority, and omit the Execution thereof: In this caſe, you may Elect another Atturney. The King was bound by his Office to execute the Lawes; it was below the <hi>Commons</hi> to pray any thing of him; they did but betray themſelves in ſo doing. The words of the Oath of the Coronation are expreſly theſe; <hi>I do ſwear to Govern according to ſuch Lawes as the People ſhall chooſe to be Governed by:</hi> And therefore when he refuſed ſo to do, the Commons might have laid him aſide, and elected another; for either his doing more, or for his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſs, then he ought to do. To prove this, I ſhall give an Inſtance out of what hath been written by Mr. <hi>Will. Prynne,</hi> (one that the Authour hath a very high Eſteem of; bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is for his laſt depraved writings, in which he hath laid aſide his Reaſon, and onely exerciſeth his Paſſion, as may ſoon be diſcerned by comparing his late Railing, wording, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable works, with his former Laborious and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy writings) in his <hi>Soveraign Power of Parliaments,</hi> as in the 4th Part. page 201. <hi>Kings</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are of no more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, then any other Inferiour Magiſtrates, Officers, or Princes whatſoever; the Scriptures do abundantly evidence, that they are queſtionable and Cenſurable, and depoſable for their Tyranny and wickedneſs.</hi> Alſo a little farther, from a Caſe ſtated touching the Clergy, he doth infer, <hi>That the King may be executed alſo.</hi> Other proofs to this Aſſertion I could produce, but I ſuppoſe he will take it better from his hand then any other.</p>
            <p>Page the 2d. This Authour deſcribeth the power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments to conſiſt,
<list>
                  <item>1. In making Lawes for the good of the people.</item>
                  <item>2. According to the Ancient Cuſtome.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, from hence he concludeth, <hi>That the Parliament are not to make Lawes to undo the People, nor perpetuate Heavy bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens:</hi> There is no man that is in his Wits will ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168631:4"/> and no doubt but the <hi>Parliament</hi> will do otherwiſe; this Authour cannot charge them as yet with that. 'Tis true, that the charge of the late War hath been heavy; that the Care of the management of the War prevented them of ſettling the Government of the Nation; that they ſhould diſſolve before, is unreaſonable to expect: beſides, their own Vote hath decided that Controverſie, viz. <hi>That this Seſsion ſhall determine,</hi> May, 1660.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he ſaith, <hi>That they are to Govern according to the Ancient Cuſtomes of this Realm, that is, to joyn with their Fellows, not to Govern Peremptorily and Sawcily.</hi> What thoſe <hi>Fellowes</hi> are, the Author mentioneth not: that their Fellowes ought not to ſubmit to Acts againſt Reaſon, that is true; it is the Reaſonableneſs of a Command, that carrieth the Authority along with it, and produceth obedience; it is for that, for the which it is to be given obedience unto: thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that are unreaſonable, are to be reſiſted. The Author here doth ſeem to conclude, That the Expelling of ſome of the Members is unreaſonable; the taking the King away, is unreaſonable; the changing of Government, is unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and the like. He further ſaith in the Sect. <hi>That the People did Intruſt the Parliament onely with Adviſing with the other Eſtates; and that the ſaid Truſt did not Impower them to lay aſide the other Eſtates:</hi> That may be eaſily anſwered by this known Maxim, <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex.</hi> When that the other Eſtates by their corrupt Intereſt did become a barr to the Peoples ſafety, they might be laid aſide by the Truſtees of the People, and thoſe Truſtees may exerciſe the Supream Authority, as in the Caſe aforementioned, made uſe of by Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> in his Aſſerting the <hi>Soveraign Power of Parliaments;</hi> That the King may be depoſed by Authority of Parliament. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, of <hi>England,</hi> was depoſed by Parliament; and <hi>Edward</hi> the third Elected in his room. Our Author citeth the Caſe of the Abbots being Expelled their ſitting in Parliament, and ſlightly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168631:4"/> mentioneth the Expulſion of the Biſhops late being expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their ſitting in Parliament: this was done by the three Eſtates. They were Members of the Parliament, it cannot be denyed, according to ancient Cuſtome, and of a diſtinct qualification from the other Eſtates, they being the Head of the Clergy: Now if that the Clergy may be expelled and excluded from having a ſhare of Supream Authority, why may not the Nobility alſo, as well as the King and the Clergy, when any or all of their Intereſts ſhall be found inconſiſtent with the Intereſt of the Publick? and more eſpecially when their Intereſt is grown to that heighth, that the preſervation of it muſt be the deſtruction of the publike.</p>
            <p>He further putteth a Caſe of a Bayliff; The which caſe would hold, if it were onely in behalf of private Intereſt; but where there is publike Intereſt on foot, it will not hold. Rules of Law can live onely in time of Peace; but, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on War and Change of Government, Neceſſities of State muſt and ever did over-rule. If the Bayliff taketh other mens goods, and keeps them for his own, he erreth: Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the unſuitableneſs of the Caſe, it ſerveth thus far, <hi>viz.</hi> If the <hi>Parliament</hi> being intruſted with the Supream Power, ſhall take upon them that power to their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and not Communicate it for defence of publick good, then they do that which is beſides the intent of their Truſt: But on the contrary, if they do otherwiſe, they do according to their Truſt; for they have no other Rule to walk by, nor limitation, than The preſervation of the People. And the ſame may be ſaid to that which he reckoneth up amongſt the Tranſgreſſions of the Times (The Parliaments Turning out of one half of themſelves) that, as for ſeveral Juſt Reaſons of State, &amp; good preſerving policy, Abbots, Priors, Biſhops, Lords, nay Kings, may be expelled the Councels of Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators, when their Intereſt doth not conſiſt with publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which is the end for which they received their being:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168631:5"/> So when the one half of a Councel ſhall conſpire againſt the other, either to overthrow the Intereſt of the publick, or to obſtruct the ſettlement of Affairs, they may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Expelled. There is none are ſo abſurd to think, That if one or two of the Members ſhould conſult or conſpire againſt the Common good, but that they may be expelled, nay further proſecuted: If ſo, it will hold good alſo in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Number: Is it not lawful for the leſſer part of the power to oppoſe the greater in that which is evil? It hath been known, that the greateſt part of a Councel hath promoted wicked Counſel? Is it not then lawful for the leſſer and better part to betake themſelves to ſuch means, as may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the putting in execution of ſuch wicked Counſel, and vanquiſh them if they can? The Law is made onely to Rule people in their diſtinct and private Capacities; and not in the Capacity of them all together, conſidered as one; In this caſe, what ſhall be a Law unto them? That is not a Law, that cannot be adminiſtred in ſuch kind of Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of State; Lawes and Preſcriptions cannot be Rules to act by; nay in ſeveral private ſmall petty Contracts, Title, and the like, there doth ( every Tearm ) ariſe ſo many Intricacies and Riddles, that all the Gentlemen of the Long Robe cannot determine ( but <hi>hab Nab,</hi> as my Lord <hi>Richardſon</hi> once ſaid ) by all the Records, Statutes and Caſes, that are Extant. Would our Authour then have ſo high proceedings as theſe ſo many vaſt Intereſts to be conſidered as in this caſe, to be made parallell and determined by the Example of a Caſe of <hi>Thomas Mouſe,</hi> and <hi>William Frog,</hi> as he doth of a Caſe between J. S. and J. N. nothing to the purpoſe in hand.</p>
            <p>He bringeth in another Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Judgment of Judge <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and Judge <hi>Ask,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Streater</hi>'s Caſe, that diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of a Parliament is a diſſolution; alſo he further urgeth his Aſſertion, That the Parliament is no Legal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, becauſe it determined by the death of the King;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168631:5"/> and becauſe that <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> did ſummon other Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the People did thereby Re-aſſume their authority, and withdrew it from the preſent Parliament. To this I anſwer, That it was no diſcontinuance at all; For ſuppoſe that the <hi>Parliament</hi> were Sitting, and by reaſon of Fire or other Accident, they ſhould be diſturbed and Interrupted, that they ſhould all fly the Houſe without Adjourning, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the next day; would this be a Diſſolution to that Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? No verily; for although it be a Cuſtome for them to continue their Seſſion by adjourning; in ſuch a caſe, the Neceſſity of Affairs requiring their preſent ſervice, they may Sit and Execute their power; and it will be as good as if they had adjourned: for adjourning is but a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and if the not performing of a Circumſtance, ſhould be a forfeiture of the power, when it is occaſioned by ſome force or accident, it would be monſtrous ſtrange, and not in the leaſt to conſiſt with Reaſon: beſides, the Kings death cannot occaſion the Diſſolution of this <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> becauſe of that Act which the Authour ingenuouſly mentioneth; which is, <hi>That they ſhall not be diſsolved without their own Conſents.</hi> That <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, did depoſe him; after which there was an <hi>Interregnum;</hi> he was dead in Law, yet the <hi>Parliament</hi> during that <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnum</hi> do Inveſt <hi>Edward</hi> the third with the Kingly Office; which was an Exerciſe of the Supream Authority in them in that Interval. I grant, that when there was no preſſing Reaſons of State for ſo doing, <hi>Parliaments</hi> did look upon their determination, at the death of the King.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth was not crowned untill the eighth year of his Reign, yet in the 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. and 6th years of his Raign, divers <hi>Parliaments</hi> were holden: the Judges of the Land did then Reſolve, That formalities muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſed with in great Actions that are above the Law; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, That it be for the good of the <hi>People,</hi> and not to their Hurt: Punctilio's of Law are to be duly obſerved in <hi>Meum
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168631:6"/> &amp; Tuum,</hi> and for preſervation of Publike peace; but they cannot in <hi>great Actions of State</hi> be alwayes obſerved, becauſe New matter and Occaſions ariſe daily, for which there is no Rule or Preſident to act by. As to the <hi>Peoples</hi> Re-aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their Authority, by Electing Other Repreſentatives, and granting their Authority to them; in this caſe, the Argument is not of Force: For that all the Conventions that General <hi>Cromwell</hi> called, were filled with Factions, by which means the Work of Settlement was obſtructed, as was evident; and a private ſecret Game a playing, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh the <hi>Stuarts</hi> Family: To prevent which, and for obtaining Settlement, there was no means left, but the again-Sitting of <hi>This Parliament,</hi> who were the only Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel fit to go on with the work of <hi>Settlement;</hi> for that they were beſt acquainted with the <hi>Reaſons of State</hi> which was the ground of all the <hi>Changes.</hi> And all other Aſſemblies drove at a <hi>Single Perſon</hi>'s Intereſt: A Conſtitution (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the preſent Condition of the Nation ) altogether tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Ruine, the diſturbance and unquiet thereof:</p>
            <p>Firſt, for that the War, lately made in defence of the <hi>People</hi> againſt the King, did occaſion ſo great an alteration, as the taking off of the King, and divers of his Friends; therefore it was not ſafe to call that Family again to the Supream Truſt, becauſe it naturally would wait for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to Revenge; and caſt about to hold the <hi>People</hi> in more ſervitude than ever they were in. If thoſe who had the power in their hands had done ſo, the Authour would have taken occaſion to have laugh'd at them; whereas now he raileth. It's natural for all, to ſtudy their own preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and when they endeavour the preſervation of others alſo, they do their Duties.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It was not ſafe to Intruſt the Supream power in the hands of any other perſon of another Family; for that would but Aſſert the <hi>Stuarts</hi> Title, and make his work more eaſie for to attempt the Supremacy; It would be m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168631:6"/> eaſie for him to claim againſt another <hi>Single Perſon,</hi> than to claim againſt the whole <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>England</hi> is ſo divided by Factions, and hath been prevented in its Expectation, that if any one Intereſt ſhould get uppermoſt, and be able to promote any other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then a <hi>Free-State,</hi> the ſeverall Intereſts cannot be ſo Equally reſpected and preſerved: There is no Government elſe that is adorned with Impartiality beſides this.</p>
            <p>If it were ſo, that there had not been thoſe Regularities obſerved, and thoſe Circumſtances performed, that in a time of orderly peace is uſed and obſerved, and that their power be not according to the Exactneſs of Rules; yet if they do the good pretended, and we attain to a ſettled Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, our Authour ſaith himſelf, he will give his <hi>Vote</hi> for them: in which he ſheweth a generous mind; and had been worthy of praiſe, had he not immediately before thoſe lines, <hi>page</hi> 11. imitated Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> in his Language. I will take notice of one of the modeſteſt of his Expreſſions; <hi>Theſe things</hi> ( ſaith he ) <hi>are done by Un-authorized and Inferiour ſpirits, ſuch whoſe whole practices have been no other but Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</hi> Our Authour ſhould here conſider, That the End Crowneth all Noble Actions, and that he cannot yet make a Judgment of the Event of Affairs.</p>
            <p>Our Authour's ſecond <hi>Quaere</hi> is, <hi>Whether as things now ſtand, it is likely we ſhall compaſse the deſign of ſetting up of a Free State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith, That the grounds and Inducements to this <hi>Quaere,</hi> are,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In reſpect of theſe that are to do it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>As to thoſe that would do it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In reſpect of the thing it ſelf to be done.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Perſons</hi> that are to do it, he ſaith, meaning the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he <hi>will warrant they ſhall not ſtand.</hi> His reaſon is, <hi>That they do not underſtand what a Free-State is; and that they are like a Ship under ſayl without a Pilot.</hi> By his favour,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168631:7"/> he is not a little miſtaken in that Obſervation. A <hi>Free-State</hi> had been ſettled long before their Interruption, but for the Care of the War, the ſtriving againſt Factions in the Houſe that were corrupted, and bribed, to betray the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the hands of the <hi>Stuarts.</hi> They do underſtand what a <hi>Free-State</hi> is; and a <hi>Free State</hi> might now be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſettled, but that they muſt Conſult all Intereſts, and equally preſerve all parties; which is a Work worthy of their Care and Wiſdomes, and will take up time: The Eſpecial good over ruling Providence of the Almighty muſt be their Pilot; their Wiſdome muſt be the Helm; and their Counſels muſt be their Sailes; their Deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be their Anchors; the ſeveral Intereſts of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they are to Reſpect as Land-marks: They have ſhewed themſelves able in the ſervice of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> they managed the late War with as much Wiſdome as ever any Councel did manage a War. They, by their wiſdom, attained to a conſiderable Reputation abroad amongſt other Nations; and therefore they are the onely perſons that are fit, and that ought to ſettle the Nation.</p>
            <p>2. As to the perſons that would do it, our Authour ſaith, <hi>It is the Army. And</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was there ever a durable Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed by an Army? And do not the M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n at</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter <hi>ſerve the Army, as the men on the Clock in</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>Abbey ſerve the motions in the Clock to ſtrike, when they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Governments have bin firſt Inſtituted by Armies, is evident; nothing of ſo great concernment hath bin more frequent then that hath bin; all Governments juſt and unjuſt are defended by Armies: ſuch Armies have not bin of uſe to a Publick, that relie not upon Council; That the Army taketh upon them the Maſtery over the Parliament, there is nothing more evident than the contrary: True it is, that the Army hath at ſeveral times made uſe of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to poyze the Affairs of the Nation; the which if they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168631:7"/> had not done, all things had bin now running in the old Channel of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> Intereſt: ſuch a thing no doubt but our Authour would have. But the Army have that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that they will not render the ſo many years of Warrs abortive, to bring forth nothing but a return to the miſery and bondage we were like to be under: but on the contrary make good their footing, now obtained, againſt all Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs, Arbitrarineſs, and Tyranny. If he meaneth that the Parliament ſerveth the Army in hearing of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes or Petitions: ſurely the Army have a right in peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning for thoſe things that ſhall tend to Settlement and quiet. The Army took up arms not as Mercenaries, but as members of the Publick, having an equal ſhare in the Intereſt of the Nation. They had be<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ayed the Nation if they had layd down their Arms, and let all have fallen into the hands of the late King, who was not render of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's good and quie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but for the advancement of his own Intereſt, making War, and is overcome, and in hold: out of which condition he is to be re-inveſted without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to account for any one irregular Action of his in Government, and reſuſing to Govern the Nation accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the advice of his great Council the Parliament. The War being ended, the King being ſtill obſtinate, the Parliament are to ſeek a way and meanes how and where to ſecure the Intereſt of the Publick, otherwiſe then by or with the King; they cannot do it without an Army ſtanding by them. They the better or the greateſt part of them have from time to time had occaſion to call to the Army for help againſt the enemies of Settlement within the Houſe: as at that time when the Speaker did flye the Houſe, one part of the Houſe invited down the Reformado Officers and rude Rabble about the City of <hi>London,</hi> who did lock up the Houſe, and forced them to vote what they pleaſed; the other part of the houſe fly to the Army, from whom was to be expected more good then could be from a multitude,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168631:8"/> in regard they were under Authority moved by Order and Council; who did march to <hi>London,</hi> guarded the forced Members to the Houſe, and excluded the others that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced this popular faction, againſt the Intereſt, peace, and quiet of the <hi>People.</hi> Our Author is to underſtand, that diſturbances boyled-up by Factions in a Common-wealth, is like to a Storm at Sea: in which the skilful Sea-man muſt furle his ſails lower, lour his maſts, laſh his helm, cloſe aboard, and lye at Try: He cannot ſayl by his Compaſs, nor keep account what way his Ship maketh. So even it is with a Parliament or Army; they cannot, untill the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of factions be allayed, and deſignes ceaſe, which cauſe Storms, Harracanes and Concuſſions by War. The Sailes, Formalities, and preſcriptions muſt be taken in; the Maſts, the Laws, Loured; in ſuch times, formalities and order, and Law, muſt be diſpenced with. Will you bring an action of Treſpaſs againſt an Army of horſe for entring upon ſuch a Medow, and feeding, trampling down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying your Graſſe? Was it an orderly thing according to Law, that <hi>David</hi> did in ſending command to <hi>Nabal</hi> for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for his Forces? I mention this only to evince what is afore aſſerted, that Law is fited for time of peace and quiet: and that ſuch actions t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at are and may be neceſſary and tending to preſervation in time of War, may be againſt Law made and fitted onely for peace: And therefore though it be not ſo Regular, it may very well become the Army to declare in what caſe they will ſtand by the Parliament. It cannot be accounted to be an appointing or a cutting out of work for the Parliament by the Army, but on the contrary their duty. An Army is not above Law, becauſe that the neceſſary execution of things relating to the duty of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, is of that high nature that it cannot come under the execution of the Laws of a Nation; therefore in ſuch caſes where the neceſſities of their affaires of truſt require them to in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rench upon that Law, they uſually are Indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſied
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168631:8"/> and pardoned, as in that of Indempnifying of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th, in the War againſt <hi>Richard</hi> the 3d (cited by Mr. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lliam Prynne,</hi> who is an Author much in credit amongſt the diſſatisfied) in theſe words: <hi>In which battle though it was juſt, and no Treaſon nor R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bellion in point of Law in thoſe that aſsiſted</hi> Henry <hi>the 7th againſt the Uſurper, yet becauſe the killing of Men, and the ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>izing of Goo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in the time of War, is againſt the fundamental Laws of the Realm, there needed an Act of Parliament to diſcharge them from Suits and Proſecutions for the ſame.</hi> 3. part. <hi>Soveraign Power of Parliaments, page</hi> 45. By all which it appeareth that an Army though they are not fit I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtruments to ſettle the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, yet they are fit Inſtruments to ayd the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Government. And to this end and purpoſe, Princes and Councels, nay all Legiſlators ever did make uſe of them? What the Army hath done in this particular, is no more then their duty; they do not take upon them the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of Government, but dutifully do adhere to the Supream Authority of the people aſſembled in Parliament; unto whoſe Judgment, Wiſdom, and Authority, the Army ſubmitteth.</p>
            <p>Again, ſaith our Authour, <hi>Durſt they do any thing contrary to the mind of the Army?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have they not anſwered that Quaere, in their taking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to give Commiſſions; the which is a thing of no ſmall Magnanimity. Our Authour is not acquainted with Politicks, he hath read <hi>Cook</hi> on <hi>Littleton,</hi> a good Authour, (I do not mention him for any diſreſpect) he deſcribeth very Judiciouſly, the Common-Law upon ſeverall Tenures; which is a thing certain. For theſe kind of Caſes, our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour ſhould read <hi>Grotius</hi> and other ſuch like, who will tell him, That a Supream Power is Imprudent, if they Impoſe or Command any thing that will not be Obeyed; or that which with difficulty they ſhall obtain to be obeyed: alſo that they ſhould diligently obſerve what a <hi>People</hi> or an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168631:9"/> would have, that, if poſſible, they may grant or give be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be asked. A Supream Power loſeth much of their authority, if the Good which they ought to do, be forced from them. It was in ſuch like points of the <hi>Politicks,</hi> that the late King loſt himſelf, contrary to the advice of his beſt Councel, who adviſed him to grant what ever the <hi>People</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> deſired.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, our Authour hath put his third <hi>Quaere</hi> thus, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of the thing it ſelf we are likely to attain to a Free-State?</hi> He ſaith himſelf, <hi>That if by a Free-State, be meant the enjoying of Liberty according to</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>chap.</hi> 29. <hi>to preſerve Intereſt, Property, and Liberty,</hi> he himſelf will be for that ſort of Government.</p>
            <p>Our Authour here hath betrayed his Ignorance, and want of knowledg of a <hi>Free-State.</hi> For his better Information, A <hi>Free-State</hi> is the Ruling of the <hi>People</hi> (by Turns) by Laws that are Superiour to private Intereſt, that may preſerve all; it is the very thing that he deſireth. Theſe things are with great difficulty and danger obtained, defended or preſerved in a <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> or in any other than in the <hi>Government of a Free-State.</hi> For thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Senates</hi> that are ſtanding and perpetual, govern well no longer then they ſee it is for their Intereſt ſo to do; The Republick is not one jot beholding to them for it. When they miſtake themſelves in their principles of Policy, and do that which is to the detriment of the People, it is then apparent; As when a wicked Prince, or a wicked Councel and a fooliſh Prince is in power, they do much Hurt to the People; when you have good from them, it is but for their own ſakes: Therfore ſome <hi>Princes</hi> and ſtanding <hi>Senates</hi> are good, not naturally or willingly, but prudentially; they ſee it is beſt to be good. A <hi>Free State,</hi> governed by <hi>Annual Repreſentatives,</hi> is Naturally good, it cannot be bad; for that no one can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in ſuch a Government opportunity to do Hurt: and it behoveth every one of them to do all the good they can, in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168631:9"/> regard they muſt Return to a private ſtate and Condition, in which they ſhall participate and be ſharers of the good they have procured, or been parties in ordaining. So that whereas it indeed is the Intereſt of other <hi>Governments</hi> to procure or permit ſome good to the People, not for the ſake of the People, but for their own ſakes; as is demonſtrated by that Aphoriſm of <hi>Machiavel</hi> in his <hi>Prince,</hi> viz. <hi>Deal out the good thou intendeſt to the People but by morſels, to keep their mouthes in taſte the better.</hi> This doth procure to the People all the good that can be procured, and preventeth all the Evil that can be prevented: and alwayes when it faileth, it is becauſe that ſome ayme at Supremacy, &amp; perpetuating themſelves, who corrupt and poyſon Councels; which may be diſcerned ſeveral wayes.</p>
            <p>Our Authour towards the End, maketh himſelf merry with Mr. <hi>Harrington;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Mr. Harrington ſpeaking well of a Commonwealth, would ſit and Calculate it for our Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, becauſe it ſuiteth with other Nations.</hi> In anſwer to this, he ſaith, <hi>That the Government and Lawes are ſuted to the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People.</hi> Then which, nothing is a greater Errour; for that the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Lawes</hi> are not fitted to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a People; but on the contrary, they are fitted to the Intereſt of the People, if they be powerful; and to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Governours,</hi> if they are more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ambitious. As for Example; Our S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Law of <hi>England,</hi> it participateth and ſavoureth of the Intereſt by which it was Inſtituted: Even as water retaineth a Tincture of the Minerals they paſs thorow: So that what was Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one Prince's Reign, was Repealed in his Succeſſours. If you let <hi>Private Intereſt</hi> grow, it will endeavour to have ſhare in the <hi>Government,</hi> and fit and ſort things for its <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency;</hi> and this our Author calleth <hi>Nature;</hi> when it is no other than <hi>Intereſt,</hi> begotten by <hi>Opportunity</hi> and other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. That a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> may be Governed as Mr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168631:10"/> deſcribeth, is certain; nay, <hi>England</hi> it ſelf: But the <hi>Intereſts</hi> on foot in the Nation maketh it Incapable: Therefore ſuch a Government muſt be made choyce of, that may beſt fit the Intereſts. Some Legiſlators have been ſo ſubtile, at this Work, that they can Incorporate (like good Alchymiſts) ſeveral Mettles into one body. If a People were to leave their own Habitation, and ſeek another Country, as the People of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> then it is eaſie to Inſtitute the pureſt Conſtitutions of Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Intereſt bears all one Date, and they receive their Stations by Let. There is no people in the World, but are apt and ſit to receive any ſort of Government, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Intereſt hath unfitted them.</p>
            <p>That the People of <hi>Englands</hi> Conſtitution is fitted for Kingly Government, it is Ridiculous to alledge. If our Authour had ſaid, That the Long Continuation of Kingly Government in this Nation had created ſo many Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Props and Pillars to ſupport its dignity, that were like ſo many Sores and Phiſtula's to the Nation: the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of which on a ſuddain, would be ſomething againſt Nature; though it was a burden to Nature, and a Diſeaſe; as of Phiſtula's to be cut out of a man's Arm, or other part on a ſuddain, it doth indanger the Patient; but apply to it Medicines to rowl and diſperſe the contagious Humours, then cut off the head of it, or make an Inciſion into it, you cure the Wound, and ſave the Patient. The like operation hath been followed here, our Authour well knoweth: and it is a Cure according to Art, if our Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion do cleanſe and fortifie the part ſo, as that no one Humour do predominate, but that all may equally per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their ſeveral Offices: The predominancy of one Humour over another, is the cauſe of Diſeaſes; and the Diſeaſes participate of the Cauſes, and are of that Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168631:10"/>
            <p>Our Authour is much heightened in his Expectation of the Fruits of an Oligarchy or ſtanding Senate; he is of Opinion, That it's the readieſt way to bring about the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing of the Intereſt of the <hi>Stuarts.</hi> Here he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers his ſecret Reaſons of State, as he doth in his Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Where he adviſeth all that are for <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> to be quiet, and make no reſiſtance: For, (ſaith he) <hi>(If you find them an Enemy, you give them occaſion to Unite; but to let them be Idle, they will diſunite and break; nay fight one with another.</hi> For this Diſcovery, I would have the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour made a Privy Counſellour, when <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the Supremacie; but not till then. Now for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of this ſubtile Stratagem, it is not according to good Rules to diſcover, and therefore it ſhall be waved.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168631:11"/>
            <head>Appendix.</head>
            <p>I Shall here add one word or two to anſwer a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pamphlet Intituled <hi>Englands Confuſion,</hi> in which the Author ex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rciſeth the Art of defamation againſt the worthy Patriots of our Country, and ſince he onely doeth it by Canting Language; it is below any ſober pen to take notice of it, onely one, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> who the Author ſayeth that goodly man, who ſo ſmoothly ſupplanted the Protector, and perſwadeth him that three Crownes were not worry a drawn Sword. Grant what the Author ſayeth, and it ſhall-affoard ſufficient matter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to that Noble Perſon who hath given ample Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the love he beareth to his Country: <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> who had the Art of well-Governing (which is ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to by Princes) once upon meditating of the corrupt and depraved condition of mankind, the abominable abuſe of flatter<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs in the ears of Princes, the inclinableneſs of Princes to hearken to them, to the detriment of a People; ſaith <hi>Suetonius,</hi> he fearing future evil, intended to reſigne his abſolute Power, and free his Country: but ſaith <hi>Tacitus</hi> I know not why he did not do it, unleſs it were out of an ambitious mind, foreſeeing who ſhould be his ſucceſſor; to wit, <hi>Tiberius;</hi> perceiving his wicked nature, it would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a higher opinion of his vertues and worth, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> miſcarryed in this point, if he had delivered his Country it had bin much more honourable in him, then to leave for his Succeſſors, ſuch abominable Tyranny as after him at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the Empire: The Lord <hi>Fieetwood,</hi> although he had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168631:11"/> the ſame opportunity that General <hi>Cromwel</hi> made uſe of to another end and purpoſe, makes no uſe of it, to ſet up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but to reſtore the detained Liberty of his Country: for which, who can complain, unleſs it be ſuch as deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a continued Tyranny, and to have ſhare of it as to Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or at leaſt to be reſpected as principal props to it: I mean as to Religion if that kind of Monarchy had bin conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, it muſt have fallen in with ſome perſwaſion or other, it would not have long continued without: then all Honors, Profits, Power and Truſts muſt have run in that Channel; which would have produced perſecution and changes of the Government, and much detriment to thoſe perſwaſions who had refuſed: Liberty of conſcience is defended and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured better in the Government as a Common-wealth, then in a Monarch. Liberty of conſcience is a thing deſired by all Epiſcopals, Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, and others, they deſire it to themſelves, but are not willing to part with the like to others: obſerve the riſe of any opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at firſt, It will cry and plead for Liberty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: but when it is grown to number, ſtrength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſufficient to preſerve it ſelf, it then thinketh it ſelf not ſafe, but in the diſcountenancing, contending againſt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring the ſuppreſſion and ruine of all other perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: it is neither ſalvation nor damnation to be of this forme, or that of any of the aforementioned perſwaſions; Salvation cometh by the free grace of God in J<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſus Chriſt, adorning the Subj<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts of that mercy with the Ornaments of Repentance, to newneſs of life, and holy and obedient wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſours of R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligion of late have loſt much of the power of godlineſs, by pu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g ſo much ſtreſſe upon the formes in which more are buſied, in deſending and aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, in putting in practiſe the duty of a holy life, which ſhall affoard more comfort at the laſt day, then the defending or being of this or that opinion.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:168631:12"/>
            <p>Now if the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> and the Army did wreſt the Authority out of his hands (of whoſe right I here ſhall ſay nothing), as would have made uſe of it by promoting one perſwaſion againſt another, in oppoſition of all other; ſince it is our unhappineſſe to be devided, did they not do their duty, and performe a kindneſſe to the reſt, and to the whole Nation, doing of that, together with reſtoring of the Nation, and making of it a free People. If it were ſo, that the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> did perſwade the Protector <hi>Richard</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, he did but his duty in ſo doing as to <hi>Richard</hi> himſelf: for that the conſtitution of his Government could not long conſiſt; it was loaded with ſo much abſoluteneſs, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions all that could be expected from it, was the making way for the coming in of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> Family; by increaſing the abſoluteneſs of the Protectors power, above whatever any Kings of <hi>England</hi> were inveſted with, to the inſupportable detriment of the People, who would have received the <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arts</hi> upon the firſt offer, on the tearms that Kings formerly held their Crownes in this Nation; and that all the Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts knew well enough; and therefore moſt of them were Promoters of this deſigne, which was the onely effectual way, nay more effectual and certain then by Armies; the which by preventing, hath ſecured <hi>Richard</hi> from thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that would have unavoidably fallen upon him by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in the Power, or upon any ſuch Change.</p>
            <p>As to the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi>'s telling <hi>Richard,</hi> that, <hi>Three Crowns was not worthy a drawn Sword; Charles</hi> the Fifth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had worn the Emperial Diadem many years, gave Lawes to the greateſt part of Europe; left his Power, as not worthy his holding of it longer. So did ſeveral other Kings and Princes, and betook themſelves to a Monaſtical life, and deſpiſed and ſcorned their Dignity.</p>
            <p>Our Authour would have had the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> given him ſuch Advice, as <hi>Philiſtus</hi> gave <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Elder, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168631:12"/> of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> he being in extream danger by reaſon of the Peoples Diſcontents; ſaith he, <hi>Dominion is a thing worthy of a man's running all Hazards to attain; and if he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth it, let him hold it: and if he periſh, let the Ruines of his Countrey be his Tomb.</hi> Which advice <hi>Dionyſius</hi> followed, and brought great Waſte upon his Countrey. If the Lord <hi>Richard</hi> had continued his T<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le, and the <hi>Stuarts</hi> could have at any time by power of Arms been able to claim his pretended Right, what Waſte and Ruine would it have brought upon <hi>England</hi> All that have read Hiſtory are able to judge, by the diſtinct Claimes and Titles of the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> This would have been <hi>Englands</hi> Confuſion indeed; what elſe that the Authour of this <hi>Englands</hi> Confuſion treateth of, is not worth the taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of; they are fully anſwered in the <hi>Continuation of this Seſsion of Parliament Juſtified,</hi> to wit, That the preſent <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> are diſobliged of all their Declarations and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and Engagements, in as much as he refuſed to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to thoſe <hi>Rules of Government</hi> as the <hi>Parliament</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for His and the Nations ſafety: and that in his taking up of Arms, and being vanquiſhed, he forſeited his <hi>Right of Government,</hi> and thereby put himſelf into a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Capacity: unto which I refer the Reader; where ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction will be given in the aforementioned Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
